(タカオ）
こういうことを2力月前 高校に入るまで俺は知らなかった
Until I entered high school two months ago,
I didn't know...
制服の裾を濡らす他人の傘
The dampness of my uniform's hem,
soaked by someone else's umbrella...
The smell of naphthalene,
clinging to someone's suit...
誰かのスーツに染みついた ナフ夕リンの臭い
The warm body pushed up against my back...
背中に押し つけられる体温
The chill breeze of the air conditioner
against my face...
顔を吹きつける エアコンの不快な風
(駅アナウンス） 新宿新宿です
Shinjuku... Shinjuku station...
新宿に到着です ご乗車ありがとうございました
Thank you for riding with us.
(タカオ）
子どもの頃空はもっと ずっと近かった
When I was little the sky was closer...
So much closer.
だから空の匂いを 連れてきてくれる雨は好きで
That's why I like the rain,
as with it comes the smell of the sky.
And often, on rainy mornings,
instead of transferring to the subway,
雨の朝はよく地下鉄には 乗り換えずに改札を出る
I exit out the station gates.
June
(タカオ）
チョコレ一卜とピールって…
Chocolate, and... beer?
でもこの人どこかで…
But, I think I've seen her somewhere...
あっ！
(ユキノ）どうぞ
Here.
Thank you.
すみません
あの…どこかで お会いしましたっけ？
U-Um... Have we met before?
え？
N-No.
いいえ
I'm sorry, my mistake.
すみません人違いです
It's okay.
いいえ
あ...
Maybe it's fitting...
会ってるかも
鳴る神の
A faint clap of thunder
少し響みてさし曇り
Clouded skies
雨も降らぬか
Perhaps rain comes
If so, will you stay here with me?
きみを留めむ
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
The
Garden
of
Words
(テレビの音声）
気象庁は今朝例年より5日早く
This morning, the JMA has declared the start of
the rainy season in Kyushu,
九州中国四国地方の 梅雨入りを発表しました
5 days earlier than average.
Nagasaki, Saga, Kumamoto,
and Kagoshima prefectures
活発な梅雨前線の影響で 長崎佐賀熊本鹿児島県といった——
広い範囲で雨が強まり 現在各地で大雨もしくは洪水…
expect strong rains over a wide area.
I'm home.
(タカオの兄）ただいま
Welcome home.
(タカオ）おかえり
コロッケ買ってきたぜ
I bought croquettes.
Great. Dinner will be ready soon.
ありがと メシすぐだから
サンキュー
Thank you.
おふくろは？
Where's Ma?
Ran out.
家出
Lucky us, we get all the croquettes
to ourselves.
ラッキ一コロッケ山分けだな
捜さないでくださいって 手紙にあったけど
She left a letter saying not to go
looking for her.
But maybe...
本当にいいのかな？
To Takao & his brother
(タカオの兄）放っとけよ
Leave her be.
どうせ彼氏とケン力して 帰ってくるだろ
I'm sure she'll be back after fighting
with her boyfriend.
部屋決めてきた 来月出てくから
I've picked out a place.
I'll be leaving next month.
Living alone?
一人暮らし？
With my girlfriend.
彼女と住む
Don't you think that's why mom ran out?
それが家出の原因なんじゃないの 母さんの
昨日話したの？
You told her yesterday, right?
ああいい加減 子離れしてほしいぜ
I wish she could just let her children go,
you know?
She's the one who's making the rounds
dating younger men, damn it.
自分は一回りも下の男と 付き合ってるくせに
(タカオの母）
いいわよ！
じゃあ私も彼氏と住むもん
Oh, yeah? Well then, I'm gonna go live
with my boyfriend!
(タカオ）
フフッあの人若く見えるからね
She's got those youthful looks, after all.
(タカオの兄）
苦労してないから若いんだよ
That's 'cause she's never worked hard
her entire life.
その分お前か'老けてくな
You're the one who's been piling on the years.
ごちそうさま
All done.
You do the dishes. I've aged enough.
俺が老けないように 洗い物よろしく
部屋が広くなって嬉しいだろ
Won't you be glad to have more space?
I guess so.
まあね
引っ越し手伝えよ
Help me move, 'kay?
Sure.
うん
ああ兄貴これ分かる?
Hey, have you heard of this?
What is this, a haiku?
何？俳句？
It's a tanka.
短歌だよ
As if.
知るわけないだろ
Ask Ma when she gets back.
こういうのは
おふくろが帰ったら聞けよ
...clap of thunder
...skies
Perhaps rain comes
If so, will you stay here with me?
(タカオ）晴れた朝は
On sunny mornings, I transfer to the subway and
head here, like I'm supposed to.
ちゃんと地下鉄に乗り換えて ここに来る
But I think to myself
"This is not what I should be doing now."
でもこんなことをしている 場合じゃないって思う
雨だ
Rain...
あっ
Hello.
こんにちは
どうも
(ユキノ）ねえ
Hey...
えっ！？
学校はお休み？
No school today?
会社は休みですか？
And your office... Is it closed today?
(ユキノ）フフッ
またサボっちゃった
I'm skipping work again...
フッ
And drinking beer in the park in the morning.
で朝から公園でビールを飲んでる
Drinking beer alone isn't good for
your health.
酒だけって
あんまり体によくないですよ
何か食べないと
You need to eat something with it.
高校生が詳しいのね
You know a lot for a high school kid.
It's not me. My mom's the drinker.
あ俺じゃなくて母が飲む人だから
I've got snack food.
あるよ　おつまみも
食べる？
Want some?
うわっ
今ヤバイ女だって思ったでしょ？
You just thought to yourself
"This woman's a freak," didn't you?
No, I...
いや…
It's okay. We're human, after all.
We've all got our little quirks.
いいのどうせ人間なんて
みんなどっかちょっとずつ おかしいんだから
そうかな
Maybe...
そうよ
Definitely.
Okay, it's about time for me to go.
じゃあそろそろ行きます
これから学校？
Heading to school now?
さすがにサボるのは
I've decided to only skip school
on rainy mornings.
雨の午前中だけにしようって 決めてるんです
ふうん
Then, maybe we'll see each other again.
じゃあまた会うかもね
Perhaps, when it's raining.
(ユキノ）
もしかしたら雨が降ったら
(タカオ）その日が
It was the first day of Kanto's rainy season.
関東の梅雨入りだった
Entrance Exam
About Tuition
(ユキノ）靴職人？
A shoemaker?
(タカオ）
現実味がないことは分かっているけど
I know it seems out of touch,
but I enjoy creating designs and making shoes.
ただ靴の形を考えたり 作ったりすることが好きなんです
もちろんまだ 全然へタクソだけど
Of course, I'm still terrible at it.
Of course...
当たり前ですけど
(タカオ）
それでもできることなら それを仕事にしたい
But despite it all,
I want to make it my career... if I can.
そう誰かに言ったのは初めて
I've never told this to anyone before.
お前何時だと思ってんだよ
Do you have any idea how late you are?
呼び出された理由は 分かってんだろうな
You know why I've called you here, right?
あっちょっと兄貴
Hey, bro...
Evenings, before I went to sleep...
(タカオ）夜眠る前
Mornings, from the moment I woke up...
朝目を開く瞬間
I realized I was praying for rain.
気づけば雨を祈っている
晴れの日には
I realized that on sunny days,
I was in a terrible, childish place.
自分がひどく子どもじみた場所に いるような気がして
With nothing but impatience.
ただ焦る
仕事とか社会とか
あの人が普段いるのであろう世界は
She exists in a world of working adults,
so very far away from me...
俺にはとても遠い
まるで一
To me she represents nothing less
than the very secrets of the world.
世界の秘密そのものみたいに
彼女は見える
はっきりと分かっていることは 2つだけ
Honestly, there are only two things
I know for sure.
あの人にとって15の俺はきっと ただのガキだということ
One: she must think of me
as just some 15 year old kid.
And two: making shoes is the only thing
that will lead me out of this place.
そして靴を作ることだけが
俺を違う場所に
連れていってくれるはずだということ
(駅アナウンス）
危ないですから
黄色い線までお下がりください
For your safety, please stay
behind the yellow line.
—番線ドアか'閉まります ご注意ください
Please be careful of the closing doors.
フウ…
おはようございます
Good morning.
今日は来ないかと思ったけど
I thought you might not come today.
よくクビになりませんよね仕事
It's a miracle you haven't been fired yet.
フフツ
Wow! Is that a shoe design?
すごい靴のデザイン？
Hey!
ああっちょっと/
だめ？
I can't see?
It's not something worth showing.
人に見せるもんじゃないから
Really?
―そうかな?
―そうです?
Yes, really.
ほら あっち座ってください
Come on, sit down over there.
I'm going to eat breakfast.
Would you like to join me?
(タカオ）
俺朝飯食べますけど 一緒にどうです？
Thank you, but I've brought my own.
(ユキノ）ありがと
でも私今日は自分の分 持ってきたの
You made it yourself?
え？自分で作って？
なによ時々作るのよ
What? I cook sometimes, you know.
Oh?
へえ
Then let's make a trade.
じゃあおかず交換しましょう
えっちょっと私あんまり…
Wait, I'm not really that good a...
んっ?
ガリツ
...cook, you know.
自信ないから料理…
白業白得よ
It's your own fault.
フフフ…
That's a side of you I didn't expect.
意外に不器用なんですね
何よ
What?
ごめんなさい
Sorry. But it's tasty in its own way.
でも　うん
これはこれでうまいですよ
It's got... bite.
歯応えもあるし
Don't patronize me.
バカにしてるでしょ
Can I have another?
もう1つもらっていいですか？
Hurry up!
(タカオの兄）早く来いよ
Wait, bro!
(タカオ）
待ってよお兄ちゃん
Takao, be careful.
(タカオの母）
タカオ気をつけて
Happy birthday, Mom!
(３人）
お誕生日おめでとうお母さん
Thank you.
ありがとう
3人で何選んでくれたのかな
What could the three of you have gotten me?
(ユキノ）ねえ
Hey... Do you think it's too late for me?
私
まだ大丈夫なのかな?
はぁ一
And you know what?
I could actually taste the food.
(ユキノ）
それでね　ちゃんと味がするの その人のお弁当
So your taste disorder has improved?
(伊藤）
よくなってきたんだな味覚障害
そんなに大げさなものでもないけど
I wouldn't go that far.
でもねちょっと前までは 本当にチョコレ一卜と
But just a little while ago, all I could taste
was alcohol and chocolate.
アル]—ルくらいしか 味がしなかったから
やっぱり思いきって仕事
辞めることにしてよかったじゃないか
I think you deciding to just quit
was really for the best.
うん　そうかもね
Maybe so.
今　思えばもっと前…
You speak to me so gently,
like you're touching something fragile.
(ユキノ）
この人はいかにも優しそうに話す
まるで壊れ物に触れるみたいに
でも息をするのもつらかったあの頃
But back then, when I found it hard
even to breathe,
you didn't believe me. You only listened to
the voices around you.
あなたは
周りの声ばかりを聞いていて
私を信じてはくれなかった
(伊藤）
じゃあ 退職手続きは休み明けに 上には俺から伝えとくよ
Then we'll start the paperwork
for you leaving after the holiday.
I'll notify the higher-ups.
うん
Okay. Sorry to cause you all this trouble
even after we split up.
別れた後まで面倒かけて ごめんね
よかったな ほんとに
I'm glad, really...
え？
About that old woman you met.
(伊藤）そのおばあちゃんに会えてさ
You know, the one you keep talking about
who brings her lunch box to the park.
誰ってほら公園の
その弁当を
持ってきてくれるっていう人
It seems like you've really struck a chord.
お互い いい気晴らしだろ？
Yeah, get some rest.
ああ ゆっくり休めよ
Mr. Itou
1 minute ago
2 hours ago
Home
1 day ago
East Clinic
Yori
2 days ago
Withheld
3 days ago
Marui
Ever since then...
(ユキノ）
あれ以来 私ー
ウソばっかりだ
...I've been nothing but lies.
ん—
Rain...
雨だ
It's raining again today in Kanto.
(テレビの音声）
関東は今日も一日雨です
ここ新宿南口でも
通勤の皆さんは傘を手に…
Here at Shinjuku Station's south exit,
the commuters all have umbrellas in their hands.
July
Here, this is for you.
(ユキノ）ねえ これ お礼
For me?
(タカオ）お礼？
I always end up
eating your food, see...
結局君のお弁当ばっかり
いただいちゃってるから
欲しいって言ってたでしよ？
And you said you wanted it, right?
こんなに局い本
This book isn't cheap...
ありがとう…ございます
Thank you... very much.
どういたしまして
It's my pleasure.
あの 俺…
Um...
I'm actually making a pair of shoes right now.
今 ちようど
靴を 1足 作ってるんですけど
Wow... A pair for yourself?
すごいね自分の靴？
I haven't decided whose shoes yet...
They're women's shoes.
誰のかは決めてないけど
女性の靴です…
でも どうもうまくいかなくて
But, I haven't been able to
get them right, and...
それで…
私ね
You know... Before I knew it,
うまく歩けなくなっちゃったの
I wasn't able to walk properly anymore.
いつの間にか
それって仕事のこと？
Are you talking about your job?
うん…いろいろ
Yeah... About a lot of things.
I don't know anything about her.
(タカオ）
この人のことをまだ何も知らない
仕事も年も抱えた悩みも 名前さえも
Her job, her age...
What worries she carries...
Even her name...
And yet I can't help but be charmed by her.
それなのに
どうしようもなく惹かれていく
(ラジオの音声）例年より10日遅く
The rainy season is officially over 10 days
later than normal in the Kanto region.
本日 関東甲信の
梅雨明け宣言が出されました
都心の現在の気温は26度
The current temperature in the city
is 26 degrees.
Like someone just flicked a switch,
the sunny days came one after another.
(ユキノ）
まるで誰かがスイッチを 切り替えたみたいに
晴れの日ばかりが続くようになった
Oh sure, now I think to myself
"I'm glad that he's not skipping class anymore"...
あの子か'授業をサボる口実が減ってよかった
なんて 今さらみたいに 考えたりはするけれど
But in reality...
でも本当は
梅雨が
明けてほしくなかった
...I wish the rainy season had never ended.
あっ
広い公菌だね
This park sure is big.
I can't believe we're in Shinjuku.
新宿とは思えないな
Oh, pardon us.
あっすいません
いいえ
Go ahead.
These are the Japanese gardens, right?
ここが日本庭園でしょ？
次 どこ行こうか？
Where should we go next?
Isn't there a greenhouse?
Let's check it out.
温室があるんだろ？
行ってみない？
見たい 見たい
(ユキノ）
晴れの日のここは 知らない場所みたい
It's like a totally different place
on sunny days.
(兄の彼女） お疲れさま
Thanks for the help.
Hey, why don't you eat dinner with us, Takao?
ねえタカオくんも 一緒に食事行かない？
すみません 今日バイ卜なんです
Sorry, but I've got my part-time job today.
This late?
これから？
お邪魔しちゃ悪いし
And I don't want to impose.
The opposite! I'm going to be living with him
from now on, so just this once...
逆よ
私これからずっと
あの人と2人なんだから今日くらい
(タカオの兄）おい 聞こえてるぞ
I can hear you.
(タカオ）それじゃ また
Well then, see you later.
かわいい子だよね
He's a cute kid.
Did you notice his shoes?
気づいた？あいつの靴
They're handmade.
あれ手作りだぜ
えっ ウソ！
What? Seriously?
不格好なモカシンだけどな
Just some ugly moccasins, though.
He's got a bright future, doesn't he?
将来楽しみじゃない？
私の靴も作ってくれないかな
I wonder if he'd make shoes for me?
どうかな
10代の目標なんて3日で変わるから
Who knows? Teenagers' interests
change on a whim...
(タカオ）
兄が家を出て
雨が降らない日ばかりが続き
My brother moved out, and
the rainless days continued.
あの場所に行く口実ができないまま 夏休みが来た
I had no excuse to head to that place.
And then, it was summer vacation.
August
(タカオ）
夏休みにはほとんど每日バイ卜を入れた
I worked part-time almost
every day over the summer.
Hmm, maybe chicken with cashew nuts?
じゃあ
鶏肉のカシュ一ナッツ炒めとか
― おいしそう
― おいしそうね
Looks good to me.
Indeed. We'll order it.
じゃそれもらおう
(タカオ）
専門に行くための学費を 少しでも貯めておきたかったし
I wanted to earn what I could
for tuition to a vocational school.
道具にも革にも金はかかる
Tools and leather cost money, too.
Sure, I missed her, but...
あの人に会いたいと思うけれど
その気持ちを 抱え込んでいるだけでは
I think it's clinging to those feelings
that is keeping me a little kid.
きっといつまでもガキのままだ
That's why I've decided to create shoes
that'll make her want to get up and walk.
だから何よりも俺は
あの人がたくさん歩きたくなるような 靴を作ろうと
そう決めた
What~ will the weather~ be tomorrow~?
(ユキノ）明日天気にな一れ
(ユキノ）27歳の私は
I'm not even a bit smarter at the age of 27
than I was at the age of 15.
15歳の頃の私より少しも賢くない
私ばっかりずっと同じ場所にいる
I've always been here,
stuck in the same place.
September
It's just like Tsukishima...
(生徒八）
困っちゃってさ
ほんとツキシマらしいよな
to have got that confused for a week!
1週間も勘違いだぜ
(生徒日）英語の課題は平気だよ
English class is no big deal.
(生徒C）キソセン甘いからな
That's 'cause Kiso's a pushover.
(佐藤）秋月くん
Akizuki!
よお 久しぶり
Hey, long time no see.
Looks like you guys got a tan.
お前たち焼けたな
Yeah, we went to the beach a bunch.
エへ結構 海に行ったからね
You're still as pale as ever.
(松本）
お前は相変わらず白いな 夏休みどうしてた？
What'd you do over summer break?
―ずっとバイト
―ずっと？
Worked the whole time.
The whole time?
That's a lonely way to spend
your high school days.
(松本）寂しい高校生活だな
学校バイ卜家事
School, part-time job, housework.
(タカオ）適当にサボってるよ
I skip school sometimes!
Now that you mention it,
you are late a lot, Akizuki.
(佐藤)
そういえばよく遅刻してたよね 秋月くん
Yup, this guy never shows up
for 1st period when it rains.
そ！こいつ雨の1限は来ない
I've got a condition where I can't ride
the subway on rainy mornings.
雨の朝は地下鉄に 乗れなくなる病なんだ
Whatever, weirdo.
ふざけんなよ
Teacher's Office
えっ
はっ
えっ ユキノ先生？
Miss Yukino?
先生
Miss Yukino!
Sato...
佐藤さん
Miss Yukino...
(伊藤）佐藤後にしてくれ (生徒たち）先生 ユキノ先生
Sato, save it for later.
Miss Yukino!
ほらお前たちも
Same goes for the rest of you.
I'm sorry, everyone.
ごめんねみんな
I'll be here until after 5th period.
5限の後まではいるから よかったら後で
After that, I'd be happy to.
Yukino came to school?
ユキノちゃん 学校に来たんだな
(松本）
ユキノちゃんが学校辞めるって話 知らない？
You didn't hear about Yukino quittin'?
知らない
No. I didn't even know who she is.
誰かも知らない
お前のクラスの古典 竹原ジイだったか
You have old man Takehara for lit, right?
ユキノちゃん3年の女子たちと ずっとモメてたらしいぜ
Yukino was always having trouble
with the 3rd year girls.
Yeah, but Miss Yukino
didn't do anything wrong.
ていうかユキノ先生は 全然悪くないのよ
(佐藤)
誰かの彼氏がユキノ先生に 惚れちゃったとかでさ
Someone's boyfriend fell for Miss Yukino,
and as payback everyone in the class
treated Miss Yukino terribly.
逆恨みしてクラス全員で 散々先生に嫌がらせして
親にまでデタラヌな噂 ばらまいて
They spread so many rumors
even her parents heard about them.
学校に来れなくなるまで 追い込んで
It went so far she couldn't
come to school any more.
ユキノちゃん優しすぎるんだよ
Yukino's just too kind. She should have
brought it right to the police.
あそこまでされたら
いっそ警察に届け出りゃよかったんだ
私たち伊藤先生とかに 何度もそう言ったのよ
We told Mr. Itou again and again!
But he didn't want to make trouble
for the school in public.
でも結局学校だって 大ごとにしたくないから…
(松本）おい どうした？
Hey, what's the matter?
(タカオ）その先輩たち…
Those upperclassmen...
(松本）え？
Do you know their names?
名前分かる？
―先生
―ユキノ先生
Miss Yukino!
He totally sucks at it.
(相沢）
で そいつがぺタクソでさ
(森山）ひでえな お前
You're so cruel.
ていうか
ショウコ変わり身早いよね
But man, you sure go through 'em.
What do you want, frosh?
何だ 1年
Are you Aizawa?
相沢先輩って
告白か？
An admirer?
誰？あんた
Who the hell are you?
ユキノ先生辞めるそうですね
It seems like Miss Yukino is quitting.
はあ？
Huh?
関係ないんだけど あんな淫乱ババア
Like I care about what happens to
that slutty hag.
Who does this guy think he is?
何すんだこいつ
え？何 何？
Huh? What's this?
何だ お前
What's your deal?
グッ！
先生のところ知らせに行こう
Let's go tell a teacher...
ショウコ知らない子だよね
Never seen this kid before.
お前 何なの
あのババアに惚れてんの？
Who are you? Fallen for that old hag?
キモくない？
ユキノ歳いくつか知ってんの？
What a creep! Does he even know
how old she is?
(相沢）
かわいそうに
だまされちゃったんじゃない？
Poor guy, she must have tricked him.
でも今度は
振り向いてもらえるかもな
She might go for him now, though.
もうユキノ
教師じゃねえんだから
Since she ain't a teacher no more.
いえてる
Damn straight.
(相沢）
じゃあ感謝してほしいね
You should thank us.
I'm waiting for the rain.
(タカオ）雨を待っている
鳴る神の
A faint clap of thunder
少し響みて降らずとも
Even if rain comes not
I will stay here
吾は留まらむ妹し留めば
Together with you
そう
Yes, that's the correct answer.
それが正解
That's the right response to the tanka
I told you when we first met.
私が最初に君に言った歌の返し歌
雨が降ったら君はここに 留まってくれるだろうか？
If it rains, I wonder if you will be staying here?
そういう歌に対して
In response to that verse, I answer...
Even if it doesn't rain, I will be here.
雨なんか降らなくても ここにいるよって答えてる
万葉集教科書に載ってました
It was in the classic Japanese
literature textbook.
ユキノ…先生
Miss Yukino...
ごめんなさい
I'm sorry...
古典の教師だって気づいて もらえるかなと思ったんだけどな
I thought you would realize
I was a classic literature teacher.
I mean, everyone at school knows about me.
それに私 学校中の人に 知られちゃってると思ってたから
But you're always off in your
own little world, aren't you?
でも君は
違う世界ばっかり見てたのね
Hey, what happened to your face?
ねえ その顔 どうしたの？
I was acting like you
and drank too much beer.
先生のマネしてビールを飲んで
酔っ払って
山手線のホ一ムから落ちました
Then I tripped and fell on the
Yamanote line platform.
ウソ！
Oh, my!
ウソです
Just kidding. I got in a fight, that's all.
ケン力くらいします
私たち
泳いで川を渡ってきたみたいね
Look... It looks like we just
swam across the river.
フフフ…
きゃあ
うわっ
クシュン
I think this might...
(タカオ）今まで生きてきて
今が
...this might be...
(ユキノ）今が一番
...the happiest...
（２人）幸せかもしれない
...time of my life.
Yukino...
ユキノさん
Yes?
うん？
俺 ユキノさんが好きなんだと思う
I think I've fallen in love with you.
〝ユキノさん″じゃなくて
Not Yukino... Miss Yukino, remember?
〝先生″でしょ
先生は来週 引っ越すの 四国の実家に帰るの
I'm going to be moving next week.
Back to my hometown in Shikoku.
I made the decision a while back.
ずっと前から決めてたの
私はね
I was practicing how to walk on my own,
there in that place.
あの場所で
1人で歩けるようになる 練習をしてたの靴がなくても
Even if I'm barefoot...
だから？
So then...
だから
So I want to thank you for
everything, Akizuki.
今までありがとう秋月くん
Um, thank you for lending me these clothes.
あの…この服 ありがとうございました
I'll get changed now.
着替えます
まだ車乞いて…
But yours aren't...
あの 俺
Excuse me... I'm going home.
帰ります
いろいろ ありがとうございました
Thank you for your hospitality.
あ...
(ユキノ）うう…
うう…
I made this lunch for myself,
but I made too much.
(タカオ）
これ自分の弁当なんですけど
多めに作っちゃったから よかったら
So if you'd like...
誰のかは決めてないけど
I haven't decided whose shoes yet...
They're women's shoes.
女性の靴です…
I was acting like you
and drank too much beer
先生のマネしてビ一ルを飲んで
酔っ払フて
山手線のホームから落ちました
Then I tripped and fell on the
Yamanote line platform.
鳴る神の
A faint clap of thunder
少し響みて降らずとも
Even if rain comes not
I will stay here
吾は留まらむ 妹し留めば
Together with you
♪前奏
ああっ！
あの…
Um...
ユキノさん
Yukino, please forget what I said earlier.
さっきのは忘れてください
I was wrong... I hate you after all.
俺 やっぱりあなたのこと 嫌いです
Ever since we first met, you struck me...
最初から あなたは何だか…
イヤな人でした
...like a person I should avoid.
Drinking beer in the morning,
spouting off some random tanka at me...
朝っぱらからビール飲んで
わけの分からない 短歌なんかふっかけてきて…
You listen all day to other people talking,
自分のことは何も話さないくせに 人の話ばっか聞きだして
yet never say a peep about yourself...
俺のこと 生徒だって 知ってたんですよね？
You knew I was a student, didn't you?
That's just unfair!
汚いですよ そんなのって
あんたが教師だって知ってたら 俺は靴のことなんてしゃべらなかった
If I'd known you were a teacher,
I would have never told you about the shoes.
After all, you think
I'll never amount to anything!
どうせできっこない 叶いっこないって思われるから
So why didn't you say anything to me?
どうしてあんたは そう言わなかったんですか
You thought maybe you'd humor
the little kid's fantasies for a while?
子どもの言うことだって
適当に付き合えばいいって思ってた？
Tell me I'll never live up
to my expectations!
俺が何かに
誰かに憧れたって そんなの届きっこない
Tell me I'll never measure up to my dreams!
叶うわけないって
あんたは最初から分かってたんだ
You knew from the very beginning!
だったら ちゃんと言ってくれよ
So tell me, god damn it!
Tell me I'm in your way!
邪魔だって
ガキは学校に行けって
Tell me that little kids should
run along to school!
Tell me that you hate me!
俺のこと 嫌いだって
You...
あんたは…
あんたは一生 ずっとそうやって
It's because you act like that!
You never say what's important!
大事な言葉は絶対に言わないで 自分は関係ないって顔して
You pretend it's none of your business!
You've been living your whole life alone!!
ずっと1人で一
生きていくんだ
Every morning!
(ユキノ）毎朝…
Every morning I put on my suit
to go to school...
每朝ちゃんとスーツ着て 学校に行こうとしてたの
でも怖くって どうしても行けなくて
But I was... scared...
I just couldn't go...
In that place...
あの場所で 私
You...
あなたに
You... saved me!
救われてたの
♪言葉にできず凍えたままで
I lived on with feelings frozen, never expressed in words,
♪人前ではやさしく生さていた
And I clumsily held you in my arms on a rainy night
♪しわよせでこんなふうに雑に
♪雨の夜にきみを抱きしめた
Street flyers and broken lamps, everybody was rushing back
♪道路わきのビラと壊れた常夜燈
♪街角ではそうだれもが急いでた
It's not you but me who is to blame. I couldn't hide my own impulsiveness
♪きみじゃない 悪いのは自分の激しさを
かくせないぼくのほうさ
Lady, you started running through a deserted station
♪Lady きみは雨にけむる
♪すいた駅を少し走った
♪どしゃぶりでもかまわないと
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
♪ずぶぬれでもかまわないと
The sight of you splashing through puddles disappears
♪しぶきあげるきみが消えてく
Morning comes quicker in the back alleys, so I have to get hold of you now
♪路地裏では朝が早いから
♪今のうちにきみをつかまえ
♪行かないで行かないでそう言うよ
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
(タカオ）夏が終わり
Summer ended, and the time came to
switch to our winter uniforms...
やがて 冬服の季節が来て
期末試験では案の定ひどい点を取り
I got terrible marks on my final exams...
高価な革を何枚も無駄にし
I wasted who knows how many
pieces of expensive leather...
I worked part-time over winter break as well...
冬休みには またバイ卜をして
And every time I added a layer
to my clothing,
外出の服が1枚ずつ厚くなるたびに
I wondered to myself...
"how is she doing?"
あの人は
どうしているだろうかと思う
I don't have enough strength anymore
♪別々に暮らす 泣き出しそうな空を
♪にぎりしめる弓茧さは今はもうない
To grab onto the sky that's welled up with tears
♪変わらずいる心のすみだけで傷つくような
きみならもういらない
You are strong enough not to feel hurt because of my unchanging heart
Lady. All wet from the rain, you looked into my eyes for a moment
♪Lady きみは雨にぬれて
♪ぼくの眼を少し見ていた
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
♪どしゃぶりでもかまわないと
♪ずぶぬれでもかまわないと
♪ 口笛ふくぼくがついてく
Whistling, I walk after you
I have known you too much, just like the night when we first quarreled,
♪ずいぶんきみを知りすぎたのに
♪初めて争った夜のように
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
♪行かないで 行かないでそう言うよ
When I head out the gates and my shirt's shoulders are dry,
♪肩が乾いたシャツ改札を出る頃
It no longer rains much in your town
♪きみの町じゃもう雨は小降りになる
♪今日だけが明日に続いてる
Today, only, continues into tomorrow
♪こんなふうにきみとは終われない
That's how you and I can never end
♪Lady きみは今もこうして
Lady, even now you still
don't even open up a little umbrella...
♪小さめの傘もささずに
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
♪どしゃぶりでもかまわないと
♪ずぶぬれでもかまわないと
♪しぶきあげるきみが消えてく
The sight of you splashing through puddles disappears
♪路地裏では朝が早いから
Morning comes quicker in the back alleys, so I have to get hold of you now
♪今のうちにきみをつかまえ
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
♪行かないで 行かないでそう言うよ
♪どしゃぶりでもかまわないと
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
♪ずぶぬれでもかまわないと
♪ 口笛ふくぼくがついてく
Whistling, I walk after you
I have known you too much, just like the night when we first quarreled,
♪ずいぶんきみを知りすぎたのに
♪初めて争った夜のように
♪行かないで行かないでそう言うよ
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
This letter has gotten quite long without me even realizing it.
Thanks so much for reading it all...
I hope you are doing well, Akizuki.
I wish the warm days of Spring would come soon.
- Yukari Yukino
This letter has gotten quite long without me even realizing it.
Thanks so much for reading it all...
I hope you are doing well, Akizuki.
I wish the warm days of Spring would come soon.
- Yukari Yukino
This letter has gotten quite long without me even realizing it.
Thanks so much for reading it all...
I hope you are doing well, Akizuki.
I wish the warm days of Spring would come soon.
- Yukari Yukino
I was practicing how to walk, too.
I believe that now.
(タカオ）
歩く練習をしていたのは きっと俺も同じだと今は思う
いつかもっと
One day, when I can walk
much farther on my own...
もっと遠くまで 歩けるようになったら
...I will go see her.
会いに行こう